(upbeat music)
- Hello everyone and
welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
- My name is Katherine.
And today we have an upper
intermediate level lesson.
It's kind of bitter, it's a little bit
sad, but it's also kind of sweet.
- That's right, we have a lesson today
all about getting a divorce
or divorcing someone.
- Yeah, so this is what happens
when two people's marriage
ends, they decide they want to
lead each other, they have a divorce.
So let's take a listen to today's
dialogue and we back in a moment.
(upbeat music)
- Joanne, let's not make this divorce any
more acrimonious than it already is, okay?
Let's just get down to
business and start dividing this
stuff up fairly so we can go
our separate ways, all right.
- Fine with me, I just
want to get this over with.
It's important we make a clean break.
Oh, I should have signed a pre-not.
- What was that?
- Nothing, anyway, you're right.
There's no reason this has to be nasty.
- My lawyer tells me that you've accepted
our alimony proposal and the division of
property as well as the custody agreement.
I keep the cat and you
get the dog, so that's done.
Finally.
- Well, let's not go there, Joanne.
Okay, so let's start with
the record collection.
I'll take the albums I contributed and you
can have your cheesy disco albums back.
- Fine, but I'm keeping the antique
gramophone as my grandfather gave it to me.
- I believe that was a wedding present
to both of us, Joanne,
and you hardly ever use it.
- He's my grandfather, and he
never really liked you anyway.
- Whatever.
- All right, I'll concede
the silly gramophone
if you'll agree that
I get the silver t-set.
- How typical, when are you
ever going to use a silver t-set?
Fine, I don't want to drag this
out any more than necessary.
What's next?
What about these old photographs?
- Which ones?
Let me have a look.
Oh, well, look at that.
That brings back memories.
Remember that?
- Our trip to Italy, I remember that day.
We were going to visit the Trevi
Fountain and we got caught in the rain.
- And he looked so
adorable with your hair all wet.
I did take a picture of Easton in there
in that little alley, smiling
and laughing in the rain.
- Oh, we really did have
fun back then, didn't we?
- Oh, Joanne, are we making a big mistake?
I know our relationship has
been on the rocks for some time,
but are you sure we can't
reconcile and try again?
- I still love you.
- Oh, Jeff, I love you too.
I'm so glad we didn't have to
decide who keeps the motorcycle.
- The motorcycle, but that's mine.
- All right, we're back.
So now why don't we take a look at
six key words on language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
- Okay, Marco, this first word
is what we call an S-A-T word.
That means it's very difficult.
It's so hard that many high school students
in America study it
before they go to college.
Acromonious.
- So the sentence starts off by saying,
let's not make this divorce any
more acrimonious than it already is.
This divorce is very acrimonious,
but let's not make it worse.
- Okay, so acrimonious would
be bitter, bitter, very complicated.
- Hard, so people emotional about it.
People, Joanne and Jeff are getting a
divorce, they're very angry at each other.
So they're not having a peaceful divorce.
This is the opposite, it's
very bitter, it's very angry.
- Can you say this test
is very acrimonious?
- No, usually relationships
are acrimonious.
For example, ever since
they had that big fight,
Jeff and Joanne's relationship
has been very acrimonious.
- Okay, awesome, so
acrimonious, a very hard word there.
As you say, many people studied to
pass exams in order to go into college.
So now you know, now moving on,
we have a very common legal term.
When people are getting married,
they want to sign sometimes a prenup.
- Yeah, you said it's common.
You hear this a lot in movies and TV.
- Yeah, I use celebrities.
- Yeah, you read about celebrities.
So basically, a prenup is a short
way of saying a prenupual agreement.
Nupual means having to do with marriage.
So basically, if you sign a
prenup, you are agreeing
to a certain conditions
before you get married.
- That's right, it's a contract
between future husband
and future wife about
what happens if they divorce.
For example, I decided
not to get a prenup with my
fiance because I don't
think we'll get divorced.
But maybe he decided
to get a prenup because
in case they divorce,
he wants to keep his car.
- Right, so it usually
happens a lot with celebrities
as we say because they
have a lot of money.
And if they get divorced
and usually it can get
complicated, how much
money the spouse gets, et cetera.
So maybe their prenupual agreement or
prenup will be that if they get divorced,
the wife may get maybe a million dollars
instead of a hundred million dollars.
- Exactly, it's a way many people protect
themselves financially in case of divorce.
- Very good.
Now moving on, another legal term
and related to money is an alimony.
Okay, so let's look at the context of
this word, Joanne is talking and she says,
"My lawyer tells me you've
accepted our alimony proposal.
" Alimony, so this is probably
something to do with money, right?
So she said that her lawyer
has proposed an alimony
and that's usually a
settlement, an amount of
money that you agree
on when you get divorced.
- Right, so this is exactly it.
In a divorce, this is how much
money one person will pay the other.
- That's right, so if
two people are married
and when they get divorced,
their alimony may be the husband,
if he's got a lot of money,
he will pay an alimony
of $500,000.
- Right, and so this is different
from property, which is the next thing.
Division of property
means that you talk about
who will receive the car,
the house, things like that.
- Okay, very good, so
very complicated situations
when you're getting divorced,
the pre-nubs and alimony,
but moving on, they were
talking about custody as well.
Custody of maybe children,
maybe custody of their pets.
- That's right, so you talk
about alimony, this is money,
property, which is things, but
what about people and animals?
- This is called custody.
I want custody, custody means caring
for something or looking after something.
You could say, the child is
in the grandmother's custody.
- Okay, so in the care of the grandmother.
- That's right.
- So usually, as well,
when people get
divorced, somebody gets
custody of the children.
- Right, so he wants custody, but he doesn't
have a job, so she will receive custody.
You could say that.
- In this case that we're talking
about custody of pets, animals.
- Right, in this case, it's
animals, but it's actually true.
People, when they get divorced, they may
ask the court for custody of their pets.
- That's right, and sometimes custody is
what makes a divorce extremely acrimonious.
- Yes, who gets to keep the
children, who gets to keep the pets.
Now, moving on in a little
bit away from legal terms,
they were dividing up
their property and saying,
"Well, I get to keep
this, you get to keep that.
" And Joanne said,
"I'm keeping the antique
gramophone as my
grandfather gave it to me.
" - Ha, so who cares
about pets and money?
I want the gramophone.
- Right.
- So this is actually a word you
don't hear very often anymore.
- It's an old thing, and that's
what antique means, right?
Antique is old.
- Right, so antique,
this is an adjective here.
It can also be a noun.
An antique table, an antique gramophone,
is something that's very old,
like 100 years old, or 150 years old.
- And a gramophone is one of those machines
that you see in movies that
play the old vinyl records
and has like a big horn
where the sound echoes.
- That's right.
So in the 19th century, early 20th century,
people didn't have CDs
or amputees or iPods.
This is how they listen to music.
So you usually have a hand
crank, you have to turn the machine,
and then the music will play, and
you can dance and do whatever.
- Right, so that's a gramophone.
Now moving on to our last word, Jeff said,
you know what, okay,
fine, keep the gramophone.
All right, I'll concede
the silly gramophone.
So to concede.
- To concede means to give up an argument.
- Okay, so you give up, you give
in, and you say, all right, take it.
- That's exactly right.
So in this case, the argument is,
who will receive the gramophone?
They fight, they argue, and finally,
Jeff says, I concede, okay, I give up.
You take it, and is it only for things,
or can you also concede someone,
like you say, somebody is right?
- You can say that, or
in election, for example,
there are two people who want to
be president, and the vote is counted,
and it's not clear who the president
is, and one person says, fine, I concede.
That means I give up, you win.
- Okay, very good, so to concede.
All right, six key words there, they're very
interesting, especially the legal terms.
Very common, and it's very, it's very
common, and it's very useful for you to know
next time you're watching maybe a
movie, or something related to this topic.
- Hopefully not the next
time you're getting divorced.
- But let's move on now to four key phrases
that we have for everyone
on Fluency Builder.
- Fluency Builder.
- Marko, let's get this over with.
I'm tired, I want to go home.
Let's get it over with.
Come on, just do it and get it over with.
All right, so this is our first
phrase in Fluency Builder
to get this over with,
or to get it over with.
- Okay, so let's take that as a
phrase, and to get something over with
means just finish it
quickly, let's stop delaying.
- That's right, this is a way to ask
to finish something
quickly, or to stop something.
So for example, I have
to go to the dentist later.
Oh, maybe I really don't want to go.
I'll say to myself, let me
just get this over with,
and once it's done, I don't
have to worry about it.
Or maybe you have homework to do,
and instead of doing it later, you're like,
okay, I'm gonna do it
now, I just get it over with.
- All right, to get over with,
to get something over with.
- Okay, and when they were
talking about breaking up or
separating, Joanne mentioned, it's
important we make a clean break.
What does she mean by making a clean break?
- All right, we hear
this phrase all the time.
It's a very important phrase.
In the relationships, it
means when two people
leave each other, you don't then call
them, or see each other, or hang out.
It means a clean break,
you stop altogether.
- Okay.
- You stop something completely.
- So you don't talk anymore,
you don't see each other anymore,
you completely just stops
contact with each other.
- Exactly, you can also say
this about breaking something.
You could say it was a clean break.
When I broke my arm, it was a clean break.
There were no little pieces
of bone or any problems.
It was a clean break, that
means completely broke.
- Okay, so when we talk about clean break
in a relationship, it means we
completely break up, we stop
talking to each other, and
it's over with, it's in the past.
- Exactly.
- All right, so moving
on, they were talking,
and completely arguing about, I
get the gramophone, I get the tea set.
And Joanne said, okay, fine.
I don't want to drag this
out any longer than necessary.
So you can hear her.
I don't wanna drag this out
any longer than necessary.
So to drag something out means
to extend, to make something longer,
to make something take
more time than it should.
- Okay, so for example, if
someone's giving a speech,
they may be dragging it
out, right, and you're, wait.
So someone's giving a very long speech,
you're like, oh my God, he's
dragging the speech out so long.
- Yeah, when will he
ever stop, or you could
say, in an argument,
I'm tired of arguing,
let's not drag this out
any more, let's just stop.
- Okay.
- So to drag something
out is usually time
related to make things
longer than necessary.
- Exactly.
- All right, and for our last phrase, when
Jeff was talking about the relationship,
he says, I know a relationship has
been on the rocks for some time.
Okay, so the relationship was on the rocks.
- Okay, so this is an interesting phrase.
Think about rocks, you see
rocks on my ground in the ocean.
Something that's on the rocks, in this case,
means something that is not going well.
Something that has
problems, yes, it's not smooth.
So when Jeff says our
relationship has been on the rocks,
he's saying we fight a lot, we
have problems, it's not working.
So if I say, my company
has been on the rocks
recently, it means it's
not doing very well.
- Business is not going well, yeah.
- So you can use this
for different things now.
Obviously, you may have heard it before
for drinks, you say, a scotch on the rocks.
- Right, that's different, be careful.
In that sentence, Mark
was talking about ice.
- Right, yeah.
- So that's different, if you
ask for a drink on the rocks.
But if you describe
yourself or your company
or your relationship as being on the
rocks, it means you're having a tough time.
It's a bad situation, exactly.
- So it's a very useful phrase.
I think that's very native, very
colloquial, if you say something like this.
- Absolutely, it's a great phrase to use.
I encourage you, I mean,
I hope that your situation,
your work and your
relationships are not on the rocks.
But I do hope that when
you're practicing speaking,
you use this phrase a
lot because it's really,
really colloquial,
like you say, Marko.
- Yeah, it's really good.
So I think we've taken a
look at a lot of phrases,
a lot of vocab, why don't we go back,
listen to the dialogue for one last time.
- Joanne, let's not make this divorce any
more acrimonious than it already is, okay?
Let's just get down to
business and start dividing this
stuff up fairly so we can go
our separate ways, all right.
- Fine with me, I just
want to get this over with.
It's important we make a clean break.
Oh, I should have signed a pre-nup.
- What was that?
- Nothing.
- Anyway, you're right, there's
no reason this has to be nasty.
My lawyer tells me that you've
accepted our alimony proposal
and the division of property, as
well as the custody agreement.
I keep the cat and you
get the dog, so that's done.
Finally.
- Well, let's not go there, Joanne.
Okay, so let's start with
the record collection.
I'll take the albums I contributed and you
can have your cheesy disco albums back.
- Fine, but I'm keeping the antique
gramophone as my grandfather gave it to me.
- I believe that was a wedding present
to both of us, Joanne,
and you hardly ever use it.
- He's my grandfather and he
never really liked you anyway.
- Whatever.
- All right, I'll concede
the silly gramophone
if you'll agree that
I get the silver t-set.
- How typical when are you
ever going to use a silver t-set?
Fine, I don't want to drag this
out any more than necessary.
What's next?
What about these old photographs?
- Which ones?
Let me have a look.
- Oh, well, look at that.
That brings back memories.
Remember that?
- Our trip to Italy, I remember that day.
We were going to visit the Trevi
Fountain and we got caught in the rain.
- And he looks so adorable
with your hair all wet.
I did take a picture of yeast in there
in that little alley, smiling
and laughing in the rain.
- Oh, we really did have
fun back then, didn't we?
- Oh, Joanne, we're making a big mistake.
I know our relationship has
been on the rocks for some time,
but are you sure we can't
reconcile and try again?
- I still love you.
- Oh, Jeff, I love you too.
I'm so glad we didn't have to
decide who keeps the motorcycle.
- The motorcycle, but that's mine.
(upbeat music)
- All right, we're back.
So a very interesting
dialogue, all about divorce.
Now, this is a very
common situation nowadays
in many countries such as
the United States or Europe.
Divorce rates are very high
lately like in the past 10, 20 years.
- Yeah, they do say
that since maybe the 70s
or 80s divorce rates
have been on the rise,
I think the average now
in America is about 50%.
- Yeah, it's like five in 10
marriages and in divorce.
- That's right.
- And then from what
I understand or I read
once, I think out of those
50% that get divorced,
if they remarry, again, the probabilities
of those that get remarried are again half.
So most likely people will
get divorced at least twice.
- That's true.
Although sometimes you meet people who
got married when they were very, very young
and they realized that
they grew up a little bit
and their personality
changed or their goals changed
and they divorced that
one time but then later in life
when they marry again, they know who they
are, they get married again, it's better.
So I think the situations
are all quite different
but it is true that there are
a lot of divorces in America.
What about Ecuador though?
I mean, is the divorce rate similar?
- No, not really.
I think people are still a
little bit more old-fashioned
in that sense, like it
was before, you know,
it was even a little bit
taboo to be divorced.
- Yeah.
- But I don't think people
get divorced as often
especially if people have
been together for quite a while.
That's one of the things
that surprises me a lot is
I've met people who have been married
20, 30 years and then get divorced.
It's like why is it like
you've been through
the toughest times, you know,
you've pretty much beat the odds
and why do you get
divorced at such a late age?
- Yeah, it does seem counterintuitive
but it's possible that they
were unhappy for that time
and they didn't want to
affect their children's lives.
- Right, man.
- And so when their
children go to college or leave,
they say, okay, now I
can make a big decision.
- I know in countries, for example,
such as Chile, divorce is still illegal.
I think in the Philippines as well.
- Really?
- Yeah, it's still illegal to get divorced.
- Is that because they're
very religious countries?
- Um, I know Chile is
not really that religious.
I don't know what it is exactly by law
but a lot of people, I
think it may be legal now.
I can't really remember very well.
I think one of our Chilean
listeners can help us out here
but I know a lot of people used to
annull their marriages because of this.
- I see.
- So they would be like,
oh, I put the wrong address.
So, no, this marriage is
not valid or stuff like this.
- Or I spelled my name wrong.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Interesting.
Well, I'd be curious to know, as you said,
whether or any of our Chilean
friends know more about this
or for the rest of you, in your
country is divorced common.
Is it uncommon?
Are there laws that prohibit
or that allow divorce?
Let us know on our website, EnglishPod.com.
- All right, we'll see you guys there.
Bye, bye.
(upbeat music)